我会很感激的。好了
I'll be grateful okay
今天我想跟大家分享一下我对Javascript数字问题的思考
today I'd like to share with you some of the questions I was asking myself about numbers in JavaScript
昨天Brendan Eich（JS的作者）在分享中告诉我们
because even Brendan Eich yesterday and his keynote
Javascript中的数字并不完美
told us that the numbers are not really perfect currently
所以Javascript以后的版本中会引入新的数字类型
that's why all these new types of numbers are being introduced for future versions
但今天我想把注意力集中在现有的Javascript中数字的实现
but today I like to focus on what currently we have in JavaScript in terms of numbers
因为当你做十进制小数或者大数的运算时
because if you ever tried to do some computations on decimal fractions or large integers in JavaScript
你可能会注意到结果并不精确
you probably noticed that they are not really precise
有时候结果甚至出人意料
and may lead to some quite unexpected results
我举几个例子
let me give you some examples of that
如果我们计算0.1 + 0.2
if we try to add 0.1 to 0.2
你可能认为结果是0.3
you would expect it will be equal to 0.3
实际上并不是
but it's not
不是0.3，而是非常接近0.3的一个数
what it's actually equal a number very close to 0.3
另一方面，如果你拿一个非常大的数
on the other hand if you take quite a large integer
比如这个，在它的基础上加1
like for example this one and you try to add one to it
结果还是原来的数字不变
you will get exactly the same number
但如果在它基础上加2，结果就对了
but if you add 2 to it you get the result as expected
但问题不仅仅是这些计算结果不精确
but it's not only about inaccurate results of some computations
Javascript中的数字还有其他怪异的地方
there are many different weird things about the numbers in JavaScript
像是有名的NaN
like this infamous NaN value
一般你做了非法的数字运算时，Javascript会返回NaN
so NaN is a value you will get if you try to turn in to a number something that is not
所以我们来试试这个
so let's try something like this
但是如果你 typeof NaN
but if you try to check the type of NaN
NaN的类型实际上是数字it will tell you it's a number
所以每次我碰上这种问题
and every time I stumbled upon something like this happening
我就会问我自己为什么
I was asking myself why does it happen
因为背后肯定有原因的，对吧？
because there has to be a reason right?
这种奇怪的行为不会无缘无故的发生，多数情况下
things like that don't happen without the reason at least in most cases
当我们有和Javascript相关的问题时
and if you're asking yourself a question about JavaScript
我们有一个确定的地方能找到答案
there is one sure place to look for the answer
ECMAscript规范
the ECMA script standard
但规范里只是说
but all the standard says about the numbers is that
Javascript数字使用双精度64位IEEE 754规范的浮点数表示法
they are represented by the double precision 64-bit format IEEE 754 binary floating-point arithmetic
事实上还有多一点解释
actually yeah it's just a little bit more than that
但没有写Javascript中，数字在内存中是如何表示的
but nothing about how the numbers are represented in the memory
也没有解释计算是怎样完成的
how the calculations are done
所以我进一步调研，发现Javascript并不是第一个使用IEEE 754规范的
so I had to look the further but it turns out that javascript is not the first language that uses this standard
有许多其他的语言也使用了这个规范
there are many others
如果你用Python，会得到一样的结果
if you try for example Python we have exactly the same problems in here
更新一些的语言，比如Ruby，也是一样的结果
something more modern like Ruby nope
当然，还有Java
and of course Java
事实上我还需要写一个类来完成这个计算
actually I had to read write a class to add these two numbers in Java
事实是
anyway it turns out that
Javascript中数字的问题就是从Java中来的
we have these kind of numbers in JavaScript because they were in Java at the first place
好，所以我问自己这些问题为什么存在
right so I was still asking myself why does it happen
我们对数字的表示出了什么问题才会导致不精确的计算结果呢？
what is wrong with this representation of the numbers that we have such imprecise results
第一步我想看到Javascript数字是如何用二进制来表示的
and the first step I wanted to make was to see how a given number looks like in this binary representation
我想看到64位表示法中的每一位
I wanted to see every single bit of this 64 bit representation
不幸的是，我们无法简单获取到内存中的二进制位
unfortunately in JavaScript we don't really have easy direct access to bits in memory
借助于我朋友**的帮忙but with a little help from my friends typed our eyes
我自己写了个方法
I was able to create myself a little utility function
所以我们可以把任何数字，比如0.3
so now we can turn any number let's say our 0.3
用二进制的来表示
and see how it looks in its binary representation
这就是0.3用64位双精度浮点数的二进制表示法
so these are all 64 bits of binary representation of number 0.3 in this double precision floating point
我们来比较下它和0.1加0.2的结果
so let's compare it to result of the computation of 0.1 plus 0.2
几乎是一样的，但仔细看右边后三位
it's almost the same but if you look at the last three bits on the right side
你会看到差异
you will see that there is a little difference there
我们可以拿任意一个数
and yeah we can take any number we want like I don't know
比如20130109，看看是如何表示的
2013 0 9 and see how it looks like
但只看这些0和1，我们无法理解
but looking at these 0s and 1s doesn't really give us any kind of understanding
发生了什么，数字是怎么计算的
what is going on there how these numbers are computed
幸运的是，由于这个规范被很多语言采用
fortunately because this standard is used in many languages
网上有很多资源让我们了解这个规范
there are quite a few resources online that tell us how does the standard work
这里我收集了一些
I gathered a couple of these here
但不幸的是，这里充满了疯狂的公式和二进制数的运算
but unfortunately they are full of crazy equations and operations on binary numbers
我花了很多个夜晚，看了大量论文才真正理解了它是如何工作的
and it took me quite a few long evenings a lot of paper to get my head around how it really works
所以今天我帮你们省下一些麻烦
so here I am to save you the trouble
希望你们听完之后能理解这一页wik
iand hopefully after this talk you will actually be able to understand this Wikipedia page
我们来看看计数法是如何工作的
so let's see how this representation works
像我前面提到的那样，我们用64位来表示数字
so as I already mentioned a couple of times we have 64 bits to represent our number
这64位可以分成三部分来看
and they can be divided into three parts
第一部分是1位符号位，在这里
there is one bit for a sign - is this guy in here
表示数字是正数还是负数
it tells us if the number is positive or negative
右侧的52位，实际上是53位，有一位是隐藏的
there is this big chunk on the right 52 bits actually it's 53 because one of them is hidden
我后面会讲到这儿
I will talk about this guy later
这一部分叫做有效数字，如果你说美式英语，你可能会叫它mantissa
this part is called significant if you are American English user you probably call it mantissa
有时候也被叫做小数部分
sometimes it's referred as fraction
基本上这52位表示数字的值
but basically this 52 bits are representing the binary digits of our number
一部分用来表示数字的整数部分
and some of them are used to represent the integer part of our number
另外一部分是小数部分
and the others are for the fraction
这里我用一个圆点将它们分隔开来
and I use this point in here to show where this split happens
圆点左边表示整数部分
so this bits on the left of this point are used to represent the integer part
圆点右边表示小数部分
and the rest is for the fraction
余下的11位是底数。 底数相当于一个乘数
and the remaining 11 bits is the exponent and the exponent is kind of a multiplier
用来和有效数字相乘，最终结果就是我们的数值
that is used to scale the value given by the significant to give us the final value of our number
我知道这很难理解，所以让我来举个例子
and I'm pretty sure it's quite confusing at this point so let me give you a little bit of analogy
我想你肯定见过数字写成这样的形式
I hope that you've at least at some point of your life seen a number written like this
这叫做科学计数法
it's so called exponential or scientific notation
这种计数法里面我们把一个数字分为两部分
so in this notation we also have a number divided into two parts
一部分是有效数字
this is there is this part it represents the significant digits of our numbers
数字中所有的数位，也叫做有效数字so all the digits we want to have in our number and it's also called significant
我们将这个数字乘以10的n次方，最终结果就是我们的数字
and we compute number by multiplying it times 10 to the power of the exponent
所以说底数相当于一个伸展的因子
so the exponent is kind of a scaling factor
底数越大我们的数值就越大
so the bigger the exponent gets the bigger our number will be
底数越小，我们的数值也越小
and the smaller the exponent gets the smaller value of our number will have
底数的大小影响圆点的位置
and we can look at this exponent as kind of defining the position of the point in our representation
因为底数变大时圆点向右移
because when the exponent gets higher the point kind of moves to the right
数字也就越大
and makes this number bigger
底数变小，圆点向左移
and when the exponent gets smaller it kind of moves the point to the left
数字也就越小
making the numbers smaller and smaller
二进制表示法中的有效数字和指数部分和科学计数法中相同的
and actually the roles of significant and exponent in this binary notation for the floating point numbers are exactly the same
所以我们倒回去仔细研究一下它是如何工作的
so let's get back to it and see how it works and more details
符号位就不用多说了
so the sign bit there is not much to say about this guy
i如果符号位是0，说明是正数
f its value is zero the number is positive
因为计算的是-1的0次方
because it's counted as the power of minus one
如果符号位置为1
and if we turn it to one
就变成负数了，很简单
our number becomes negative simple as that
指数部分比较有意思
exponent is a little bit more interesting
我们有11位来表示指数部分
so we have eleven bits to represent the exponent
指数幂是一个整数，所以可以表示0到2047之间的数
and the exponent that is an integer value so we can represent the number from 0 to 2047
但是因为我们想让指数幂可以是正值或者负值
but we would actually want exponent to have negative and positive values
所以这里实际上使用的是移码表示法
so what is actually used in so called offset binary notation
我们计算和2的指数幂乘积
so we take the number computed from the powers of two
得到指数幂，然后减去1023
of the from the bits of exponent this one and we subtract 1023 from it
it's exactly the health of the range so when our value computed from the exponent
bits gets exactly to this point of 1022 three our exponent will be zero
当它的值变小，指数幂就是负值
and when it gets lower, the exponent will be negative
当它的值变大，指数幂就是正值
when it's higher the exponent will be positive
这个数，指数幂的值
and this number, the value for the exponent
实际上定义有效数字部分小数点的位置
is actually defining the position of this point in the significant
它决定了多少位是整数部分，多少位是小数部分
so it defines how many bits we have for the integer part of the number and how many are left for the fraction part
指数幂越大，整数部分的数位越多，数值越大
so the bigger our exponent gets the more bits we have for the integer part and the bigger our integer value gets
指数幂越小，小数点向左移，整数部分的数位变少
the smaller exponent is the point will move to the left making/giving us less bits for the integer part
这就是为什么叫做“浮点”数
and actually that's why it's called the floating point
因为小数点的位置是变化的，取决于指数幂的值
because the position of the point is depends on the value of the exponent
现在来看看最重要的部分
so now let's have a look at the most important part
有效数字
the significant
之前说过了，有效数字有52位
as I told you already we have 52 bits
这些红色的数字，第一位是隐藏的
these are these red ones and here this first guy is this hidden
我们将它放在这儿
we can save him here yeah and we can stick him
因为我们不能控制它的值
because we don't actually control its value
它的值永远是1
its value is always assumed to be one
所以我们不把它算作64位的一部分
so that's why we don't have to put them into 64 bits
因为我们不能把它的值变成1
because we can't change it to 0
为了解释有效数字部分是如何工作的，先来点简单的，比如1
so to explain you how this significant works let's start with something simple like number 1
对于数字1来说，指数幂部分为0
so for number one our exponent is zero
所以小数点的位置在这里，它的左边有1位
so it puts our point in here so we have one bit on the left hand side
这一位表示的是整数部分
this one bit representing our integer part
表示2的0次幂
and it represents two to the power of zero
等于1，因为现在仅有一位表示整数，所以无法表示更大的数
so it's 1 but we have only one bit for the integer we can't represent any bigger number
如果我们想表示数字2
so if we try to represent the number 2
我们需要将小数点向右移动，通过改变指数幂
we have to move the point to the right by changing the exponent
现在呢我们整数部分有两位了
so now we have two bits for the integer part
第一位表示2的1次幂
this first bit is representing 2 to the power of 1 at this point
等于2
so it gives us 2
另一个表示2的0次幂
and the other one is representing 2 to the power of 0
于是我们得到了数字3， 但是同样，我们的整数部分只有两位
so we can represent also number 3 but again we just used our 2 bits in the integer part
为了表示数字4，我们需要再一次将小数点向右移，通过改变指数幂
so to represent number 4 we have to again move the point to the right by changing the exponent
so now we have oops sorry yeah I was at for ideas
于是现在我们整数部分有3位了
so now we have three bits for the integer part
第一个表示2的2次幂
the first one represents two to the power of two
最后一个表示2的0次幂
the last one represents two to the power of zero
所以数字越大，我们需要的整数部分的位越多
so the bigger number we want to represent in terms of the integer value the more bits we will need for the integer part
现在我们来看看小数部分
now let's see how the fraction part works
小数点后第一位表示2的-1次幂
the first bit after the point represents 2 to the power of minus one
是1/2
so it gives us 1/2 to the power of one so it gives us a half
所以通过小数点右面第一位我们能表示小数0.5
so by changing this first bit after the point we can represent 0.5 fraction
下一位表示2的-2次幂
the next one is representing 2 to the power of minus 2
结果是1/4，下一位是2的-3次幂，1/8，后面同理
so it gives us a quarter next one is 2 to the power of minus 3 it's 1/8 and so onand so on
能看出小数部分的越往后表示的数字越小，是2的-n次幂
every single bit and the fraction part represents smaller and smaller fraction based on the inverse power of 2
这告诉我们
so what it tells us is that
我们表示的小数，必须是-2的n次幂加和
we can only build the fraction of our number by adding up these inverted powers of 2
不幸的是，并非所有十进制的小数都能通过2的-n次幂加和得到
and unfortunately not all of decimal fractions can be represented this way
我们以0.1为例
so if we take our 0.1 example
可以看出为了得到0.2，我们将越来越小的2的-n次幂加起来
we can see that to form 0.1 we are adding smaller and smaller powers of two
但事实上我们永远得不到精确的0.1的值
but actually they will never add up to exactly 0.1 value
所以说存储0.1的时候已经有一点误差
so this value is already stored in this representation with a little bit of error
我们做计算时，误差会加起来
and these errors add up when we do some computations on these numbers
在某一时刻，误差就会显示出来
and at some point they they show up
所以这种表示法导致的不精确是由于两个原因
so the limit of this representation in terms of accuracy of the fractions is based on two factors
第一个原因 我们是通过将2的-n次幂加和得到小数
first factor is that we are building our fraction from the inverse power of two
另一个原因是我们的有效数字位只有有限的52位
and the other factor is that we actually have quite limited 52 bits of significant
我们表示不了更小的数
we can't represent the smaller values
更重要的是
what is even more important is that
大整数的值
the bigger number we get in terms of the integer value
当我们在整数部分需要更多的数位时
so when we need more and more bits for the integer part
小数部分可以使用的数位就越少
the less bits we have left for the fraction part
所以当我们将小数点移到最右侧时
so when we move the point right to the end of this representation
我们来看看对于这么大的数字
let's see to this point for such a large integer value
我们只有一位留给小数部分所以我们只能表示
we have only one bit left for the fraction part so we can only represent the house
对于这么大的数来说，我们表示不了小数部分
we can't represent any other fraction for such a large numbers
如果我们再将小数点右移，会发生什么呢？
so what happens if we move the point even more to the right
如果幂指数等于52
if the exponent is equal to 52
有效数字部分所有的位都来表示整数部分
we have all the bits of the significant used for the integer value
小数部分没有数位可用了
there is no bit left for the fraction part
所以只能表示整数
so from this point we can only represent integers value
有效数字能表示的最大的整数
so the biggest integer value that actually fits into this significant
就是这个数字，我们用了有效数字的所有数位来表示这个数
is this one we've used all the bits in the significant part to represent this number
那如果我们想表示更大的数呢？now what would happen if we try to represent the bigger number
我们看看，改一下这里
let's see let's change that
和我们预想的一样
what happens is kind of what we expected
我们将小数点右移
we moved the point to the right
为整数部分多展开一位
to make a more space for the integer part
所以我们整数部分有53位， 但事实上不存在第53位
so we have right now 53 bits for the integer part but actually there is no bit left there
那这个数值是怎么计算的呢？
so how the number is computed
所有不存在的数位，都被当成0
so what happens is that it's assumed that all these bits that are missing are zeros
所以说这个数字可以被准确表示的
so this number is actually accurately represented
因为最后一位被当做是0
because this last bit is assumed to be zero
如果给这个数加1，会发生什么呢？
but what would happen if we try to add 1 to it
我们又一次无法进行加1操作，因为改变不了最后一位的值
again we can't because we can't change the value of this last bit
我们控制不了最后一位的值，它永远是0
because we don't control it it's it's always zero
我们能控制的最后一位是这个
so the last bit we actually control is this one
它代表2的1次幂，所以我们只能对这个数字加2
and it represents two to the power of one so we can only add 2 to this number
所以当指数幂等于53时
so from this point when the exponent is equal to 53
我们只能表示每两个数直到这里
we can only represent every second integer until we get to this point
为了表示更大的数我们需要再一次加2
and again to represent the bigger number we again have to add 2 to it
我们将小数点右移
we will move point to the right
现在我们有两个数位只能是0
so right now we have 2 bits that are assumed to be 0
我们能够控制的最后一位代表2的2次幂
so the last value the last bit of our control is representing 2 to the power of 2
是4
so it's 4
所以当指数幂等于54时，我们只能每4个数表示一个
so we can represent only every 4th integer for exponent equal to 54
指数幂越大，我们能表示整数之间的差值就越大
so the bigger the exponent gets the bigger gaps we will have between the integers values
所以从指数幂等于52开始
we can represent so actually starting from this exponent 52
我们不能表示连续的整数了
we already have gaps between the numbers
所以说对于这么大的数任何计算都会发生错误
so actually any operations on on such a large integers will have some error
同样这种错误在小数里也会发生
and similar thing happens on the other side of the significant
我们让数字变小，让指数幂等于-1
if we make it smaller when we have the exponent value of -1
这时小数点就是隐藏位后面
so our point is right before the hidden bit
隐藏位表示1/2
this hidden bit represents 1/2
有效数字的其他数位表示越来越小的2的-n次幂
and every other bit in the significant represents smaller and smaller powers of 2
当我们将小数点左移
and when we move the point to left
我们得到不存在的数位，值都为0
we are getting some missing bits assumes to be zeros
所以有效数字的第一位表示越来越小的2的-n次幂
our first bit insignificant represents smaller and smaller power of 2
越来越接近0
so we are getting closer and closer to 0
但当隐藏位值是1
but when we have this bit the hidden bit assumed to be 1
它永远表示2的幂
it always represents some power of 2
值可能非常小，但是有值
it can be very small but there will be always some value in here
所以我们永远不能表示0
all right so we will never be able to represent number 0
因为这一位永远表示某个值
because we'll always have some value given by this bit
所幸这种表示法有个死亡区间
fortunately this representation has a section for death
当指数幂是最小值
so when our exponent gets his lowest possible value
指数幂部分所有数位都为0
so when the all bits of the exponent are 0
我们的指数幂是-1023，隐藏位也是0
so our exponent is minus 1023 the hidden bits also turns to 0
这样我们能表示0了，所有的数位都是0
so this way we can represent zero as all the bits being 0
当然我们可以改变有效数字的数位来表示一个非常接近0的数
and we can of course change some bits in significant to represent numbers very close to 0
这些叫做“非常规数” 因为隐藏位是0
they are called sub normal values because of this hidden bit being 0
但你可能还记得这个家伙
but you may remember this sign guy in here
我说过这是符号位，可以改变数值的正负
and I told you that we can use it to change the sign of any number represented in this representation
把符号位变成0会发生什么呢？
so what would happen if we change the sign of 0
我们得到了-0
yeah we will get minus 0
事实上浮点数表示法定义了两个0
actually the floating point representation defines two 0s
+0和-0
positive and negative one
Javascript中，-0并不常见
in JavaScript it's not very easy to notice this negative zero
只有一些特殊操作，比如除以负无穷大，才会得到-0
because there are only certain operations that return it like dividing by minus infinity
但-0确实存在，并且和+0在表示上是有区别的
but it's there and the difference between negative 0 and positive 0 can be actually detected
所以我们见过当指数幂是最小值情况了
so we've seen what happens when the exponent is again when the exponent is at its lowest value
现在我们看另一种极端的情况
so now let's see the other side of the extreme
所有的数位都为1，让指数值取最大值
when we have all the bits of the exponent set to 1 for the highest exponent value
这是为正无穷和负无穷的保留值
this is the value reserved for the Infinity positive or negative infinity
所以无穷大就是长这样
so that's how the Infinity looks like
指数幂部分都为1，有效数字部分都为0
all the exponent bits set to 1 and all the significant bits set to 0
当改变有效数字部分会发生什么呢？and what will happen if we try to change this significant bits to Banke we get to now
没有发生因为实际上发生了错误
and it's not because there is some error actually
浮点数表示法定义了NaN
floating point representation defines NaN value
所以当指数幂部分都为1时，有效数字的任意位不能为1，否则就是NaN
so if all the exponent bits are set to 1 and any bit in the significant is set to 1 it's not a number value
这解释了为什么typeof NaN结果是number
so it kind of explains why NaN type is a number
因为NaN的值使用浮点数表示法来定义的
because NaN is a value defined by the floating point representation
和数字一样，也是64位
it's defined by 64 bits like any other number actually
由于有52位的有效数字位所以NaN实际上有很多不同的值
this we have 52 bits in significance so there are quite many NaN values defined in this representation
还好Javascript把它简化为一个NaN
fortunately to us JavaScript simplifies it to only one NaN
好，我们现在回顾一下刚才所讲的
yeah but let's get maybe back to numbers and summarize it what we already heard here
对于任意数字
so for any given number we can compute its value
我们都可以通过有效数字，小数点位置和幂指数来计算它的值
by computing the values of the significant bits with the position of the point based on the value from the exponent
数字的符号位决定正负
and design defining a design of our number
正如一开始所说的，我们可以把幂指数当作放大器
but as I told you at the very beginning we can treat the exponent as kind of a multiplier
如果我们把它拿出来当作放大器
so if we take it out of this parenthesis and treat it as a multiplier
我们将它与有效数字相乘，从2的0次幂开始
we start to compute the significant value always starting with 2 to the power of 0
是隐藏位的值
it's the value given by this hidden bit
我们总可以把它置为1，因为2的0次幂是1
so we can always set it to 1 because you know 2 to the power of 0 is 1
这是由隐藏位决定的
so that's the one given by the hidden bit
这里我们得出了幂指数的值
and here we have the value computed for the exponent
通过这种方式我们反向工程化了这个公式，这个双精度浮点数计算的公式
and this way we kind of reverse engineered the equation for how the numbers are computed in double floating-point representation
这和我们在Wikipedia中看到的公式类似
and that's the equation you can find in similar fashion on this Wikipedia page
我理解在狂欢之后的周日早上这是一个硬核的话题
so I know it was quite a hardcore topic for a Sunday morning after the great party
但是我希望你对javascript数字多了一些了解
but I hope that I have given you at least a little bit of understanding how numbers in JavaScript work
Javascript中的数字为什么会存在一些问题
and why we have all these problems we've done
并且以后我们可以自认为明白二进制
and hopefully after this talk we can all think about ourselves as those who understand binary
或许下一次你被Javascript数字一些奇怪的行为难倒
and maybe next time you stumble upon some weird behavior with numbers with JavaScript
你会问问自己为什么会这样
and you will ask yourself why
因为答案就在那里，等待我们去发掘
because answers and reasons are out there waiting for us to find them
保持你的好奇心，因为你会学到好多非常有意思的东西
so be curious because there is hell a lot of interesting things you can learn
也有很多你意想不到的答案
and sometimes quite unexpected answers you can get
我说完了
so that was all I had for you
可以关注我的Twitter
you can follow me on Twitter
早上好 JSConf
good morning JSConf
所以你们都知道我的名字了
so you already know my name
我从来没看过自己名字显示的这么大
I've never seen it this big
可以帮我照个照片吗？
can someone take a picture of it for me